Doctor Who: The Five Doctors is a science fiction, action,
adventure film directed by Peter Moffatt.
Many incarnations of the Doctors and their old companions are taken out
of time and deposited in the Death Zone on Gallifrey.
There, they must battle the Master, Daleks, Cybermen and Yeti in order to
reach the Dark Tower and discover the Tomb of Rassilon.
The Doctor (5), played by Peter Davison.
The Doctor (3), played by Jon Pertwee.
The Doctor (2), played by Patrick Troughton.
The Doctor (1), played by Richard Hurndall.
The Doctor (4) (archive footage), played by Tom Baker.
The Doctor (1) (archive footage), played by William Hartnell.
Fourteen actors have portrayed the Doctor in a leading role in the
British science fiction television series Doctor Who.
The series' protagonist, the Doctor is an alien
from a species called Time Lords.
The transition to each succeeding actor is explained within the narrative through the plot device of regeneration, which
allows Time Lords a change of cellular structure when they near death, changing their appearance and personality.
The first actor to portray the Doctor was William Hartnell beginning with
An Unearthly Child (1963) through The Tenth Planet (1966).
In the final moments of the serial, the First Doctor
regenerated into Patrick Troughton's Second Doctor.
The most recent incarnation, the Fifteenth Doctor, was played by Ncuti Gatwa, who took over
the role from David Tennant following the conclusion of "The Giggle" (2023).
Gatwa departed the role in "The Reality War" (2025).
Outside of television many actors have played the Doctor in various BBC-licensed
spin-offs on television, stage, radio, film, audio plays, and webcasts.
The character's ability to periodically regenerate appearance and personality has facilitated the ability of new actors to take over the
role – in official and unofficial productions – while in most cases maintaining continuity with the television series.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking.